Inventory of the Powell Family Papers 1775-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers of the Powell Family, 1785-1927, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1860-1869. (Box 2-3)
    - Papers, 1867., 15 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
      - Hattie [Powell], n.p., to [Nina Powell?], n.p., [1862-1867?]., 2 pages. ALS. Incomplete, first part missing. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Asks about her interactions with Mr. D[?]; says Nina's happiness is the only bright spot in their lives; says she hasn't been to church much; says she has seen a lot of Willie S.[?]; regrets that she can't say everything she would like to, because the letter must go through so many hands; writes of the broken Southern spirit; asks if there are any "situations" near them that she could take; says that she cannot write much because it works her "into such a state".
    - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 29 January 1868., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Tells of their new life at Linden, helping to take care of "Sis" May's children; comments on Nina's sister Hattie's marriage; discusses religion; describes a trip to Richmond; news about family and friends.
    - Hattie [Powell], n.p., to Nina L. Powell, n.p., June [1865-1868]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Recommends that she or Rebecca go with her to visit friends in Prince Edward County; tells her that since Mrs. B[ooker's] house was used as headquarters for them during the war, they must make a pleasure visit to her since the war is over.
    - "Cousin" Emily [Forrest?], 87 North Charles Street, Baltimore, Maryland, to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 6 February 1869., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Thanks Nina for sending her the objects repossessed from the war; comments on their sentimental value; gives news about Baltimore's social events and her husband Douglas' work.
    - S[elina] Powell, Alex[andri]a, [Virginia], to "daughter" [Nina], n.p., 13 February 1869., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Tells what family has done since she left for her trip; says everyone is feeling remarkably well on account of the warm weather; tells her to enjoy her visit with Lizza and Aggie [?].
    - Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 15 February 1869., 4 pages. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Tells what each person in household is doing that evening: Mamma, Papa, Lute[?], Lewis[?], Fan[?]; says she visited Hattie who is feeling well "under the circumstances"; news about neighborhood.
    - S[elina] P[owell], Alex[andri]a, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 21 February [1869?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Describes the health of each family member; says Mr. Powell had dyspepsia for which she gives him a raw onion; says Hattie is the same and cannot leave her room; gives news of friends; discusses a fire at Lee's [?] house; hopes she is enjoying her visit with Lizzie and Aggie.
    - "Sister" Rebecca C. P[owell], Alex[andria], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 26 February 1869., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Gives news about family and neighborhood; says that Cousin Lee's house burned; writes that Bob [Robert] Powell is now a doctor; news about her school.
    - "Sister" Hattie L. P. Smoot, Alexandria, Virginia, to Nina [Powell], n.p., 28 February 1869., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Discusses news of neighborhood and people who have come to visit her; tells Nina to enjoy her stay with Lizzie and Agnes [?]; says she is still flat on her back but hopes to be better in a few weeks.
    - "Cousin" Samuel Hopkins, White Hall, [Maryland], to Nina [Powell], care of Charles Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 29 May [18]69., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Regrets that he could not make the picnic that Nina planned; says that he had to pick up Josie [?] that day, who traveled flat on her back; says that he saw "Cousin Rebecca" in town.
    - Nannie [Anne lefevere Dupuy], Farmville, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 2 October 1869., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Tells how she had been preserving many foods last summer because of the possible food shortage during the coming winter; describes her stay with "Sis" May in Farmville; describes the situation of the churches and Sunday school in her area; news about family and friends; one of Nina's students, Emma Henry, is getting married.
  - Papers, 1870-1879. (Box-folder 5:3-5)
    - Papers, 1870., 18 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
      - A. M. Randolph, Baltimore, [Maryland], to Nina [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, 15 January 1870., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Apologizes to Nina for not calling on her while she was in Baltimore; expresses her job in their friendship.
      - [Getty McGuire], Winchester, [Virginia], to Rebecca [Powell], n.p., 8 January [1866-1870?]., 8 pages. AL. Incomplete, last part of letter missing. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Writes of their sorrow at the death of Hugh [Holmes McGuire] (brother of cousin); whose wife just had a child; asks Rebecca to come visit, since the war is over; gives news about who owns the Powell's old home; tells what each of her relatives is doing; gives news about friends; discusses the death of her aunt who never recovered after the Yankees burnt her house down; mentions how many soldiers cannot find employment. [Hugh Holmes McGuire MW battle of High Bridge.]
      - "Cousin" E. H. Crenshaw, Baltimore, [Maryland], to [Nina Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 15 [February] 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Discusses Magie's wedding [her niece]; says she has been alone in the evenings since Nina left her; describes her friends who have called during the day.
      - Kate [?], Richmond, [Virginia], to "Cousin" [Nina Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 12 May 1870., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Apologizes for not writing; describes her schedule to taking care of a family of ten people; gives news about her gentlemen friends.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 5 July 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Extends sympathies to Nina and her family in the death of her sister, Hattie Powell Smoot, who died in childbirth; offers comfort through religion.
      - Jane P. Norris, Berryville, [Virginia?], to "Sister" [Selina L. Powell], n.p., 7 July [1870]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Offers her sympathy for the death of her daughter Hattie; discusses Hattie's character; mentions how Hattie has been looking forward to the time of childbirth.
      - Mary Custis Lee, Lexington, [Virginia], to Selina [Powell], n.p., 15 July [1860]., 2 pages. ALS. Xcy included. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Gives her sympathy for the death of Selina's daughter Hattie; speaks of her husband Robert, saying she thinks he may never be entirely well again; gives news of family.
      - "Cousin" Maud P[owell?], Fairfield, [?], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 18 July 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Tells of her mourning for her cousin Hattie's death; offers her sympathies; gives news of family.
      - "Friend" Belle [Smith], Cedar Mountain, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 4 August [18]70., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Offer her sympathies for Hattie's death; describes her stay in her Uncle Phil's home in the mountains; says she will return home to Alexandria in the Fall.
      - R[ebecca] C. Powell, Mountain House, [?], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 5 August [18]70., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Describes the mountain inn and how they spend their time; says the mountain air is helping their mother's health.
      - Lizzie [Stringfellow?], Springbank, St. Catharines, Ontario, Canada, to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 16 September [1870]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Expresses her joy that Nina is engaged; discusses Nina's mother's health; says she is confined to bed and in much pain; says the treatment causes much suffering and that she is anxious to leave for home.
      - "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], n.p. to "darling" Selina Powell, n.p., [29 September 1870]., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Says she is glad Nina gets a chance to enjoy herself, and visit with her cousin Lizzie, without worrying about daily duties; says her Aunt Lute is taking good care of her.
      - "Mother" Selina Powell, n.p., to "darling" [Nina Powell], n.p., 3 October [1870?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Gives a report on everyone's health; says she is feeling better; gives news of friends and family; hopes that she is enjoying her stay with "cousin" Lizzie.
      - Belle [Smith], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 5 October 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Discusses grief and religion; teases Nina about her engagement [to Sewell Hepburn]; tells her to enjoy her stay and to get well soon; news about Alexandria.
      - Lizzie [Stringfellow], Petersburg, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 8 December [1870?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        News of friends and family; describes the trouble of giving a party for a couple to be married, and wonders why people have marriages in such poor times.
      - Lizzie [Stringfellow], Verdon, [Hanover County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 20 December [1865-1870]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Pleads with her to visit them for Christmas.
      - Lizzie [Stringfellow], Mountain House, Botetourt County, [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., [1865-1870]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Reports that they have been trying both the "Alleghany Springs" and the "Yellow Sulfur" springs; says the water has helped her health; describes the social life at the springs.
      - [?], n.p., to [?], n.p., [1865-1870?]. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Inquires about her friends in Alexandria; asks if Mrs. Cassius Lee has information on household goods stolen from her.
    - Papers, 1871., 18 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], Danville, Virginia, to Nina [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, 23 January 1871., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Tells of her and Nancy's stay in Danville; discusses Nina's wedding; says her brother Abner will be in the Legislature until it adjourns; news about family and friends.
        Envelope included with list of bridal attendants on the back.
      - "Cousin" Kate Powell, Richmond, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 28 January 1871., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Discusses her daily schedule; describes a sewing machine that she bought; discusses Nina's wedding; news about family and friends.
      - "Cousin" Sue A. Grady, 69 M[oun]t Vernon Place,[?], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 15 March [1871]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Expresses her job in hearing Nina is engaged; reports that she has heard Mr. Hepburn described as "intellectual" and "pious"; says Capt[ain]. Grady sends his love; sends her a gift.
      - "Cousin" Kate S. Powell, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Nina Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 20 March [18]71., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Regrets that she cannot come to Nina's wedding; hopes that Nina will be happy living in the parsonage; news about family and friends.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], Farmville, Virginia, to Nina [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, 5 April 1871., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Apologizes that she cannot be there for the wedding; sends her money to buy a wedding present; tells that she had to refuse a gentleman who revealed his feelings for her; wishes her happiness in her new life.
      - "Friend" A. M. Fitzhugh, n.p., to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 11 April 1871., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Note accompanying a wedding present, wishing Nina happiness.
      - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, n.p., to [Nina Powell Hepburn], n.p., 14 April [1871]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Gives a report on her health, saying she is much stronger; tells what remedies she is taking; says they have given most of her wedding cake away; says that everyone thinks her wedding was beautiful; gives her philosophy on marriage and its importance; tells her how lucky she is to have found such a "good man."
        Including ALS from R[ebecca] C. P[owell] to Nina giving a report on their mother's health.
      - Belle [?], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 17 April [1871]., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Describes how she spent her Easter vacation; describes the events that took place after Nina's wedding; describes a visit to Georgetown.
      - "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], Alex[andria], [Virginia], to "darling [Nina Powell Hepburn], n.p., 19 April [1871]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Reports she is feeling better but that Rebecca has neuralgia from a bad tooth; tells Nina that she should call her husband "Mr. Hepburn"; says it is Nellie's wedding day; advises her to obey her husband now that she is no longer there to control her.
      - "Sister" Rebecca C. P[owell], Alexandria, Virginia, to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 21 April 1871., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Gives news about home and tells Nina that they miss her greatly; says the relationship between herself and John [?] is growing stronger; hopes that she is enjoying her stay in the country with her husband.
      - Rebecca C. P[owell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nine [Selina Powell Hepburn], n.p., 9 June [1871]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Discusses their mother's health, noting improvements; expresses eagerness to visit her in her own home; asks about Sewell.
      - "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 22 June [1871]., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Discusses her arrangements to come see them; says she is feeling better but she is still weak; tells her to ask for what she needs just like when she lived at home; gives news of family and friends.
      - S[elina] Powell, n.p. to Miss Selina L. Powell, n.p., [1870-August 1871?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Writes to tee her that her health has improved since she left home; gives a report on her health and what she has done there [at a resort?]; says her father will be home soon.
      - Obituary of Selina Powell who died August 4, 1871; August 1871., 2 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Includes description of S. Powell.
      - Ch[arle]s L. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Mr. R. H. McKim, n.p., 10 August 1871., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Thanks him for the letter of sympathy concerning his wife, Selina Powell; gives a detailed description of her death and a tribute to her life.
      - M. C. Lee, n.p., to Rebecca [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 21 September 1871., 2 pages. ALS. Xcy included. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Offers her sympathy in the loss of her mother; says that her mother [Selina Powell] was one of her earliest friends.
      - C. B. R[iddick?], Blackwater Boat, [?], to Cousin Mollie and Uncle Ed, n.p., 27 October 1871., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Entreats them to warn his wife Lizzie against a woman named Mrs. Hubard who he is convinced is seeking their ruin.
      - [Selina L. Powell], n.p., to one of daughters [Rebecca, Hattie, or Nina], n.p., n.d. [January 1864-1871]., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Tells of friends' illnesses and other afflictions; discusses preachers; says she will wait to buy cotton until the price goes down.
        Including incomplete AL (written on top of) of 8 January 1864 from [?] Danville, Virginia, to "sister." Says she would like to visit her and also to see her whole family but that she cannot leave because of her duties; says she can only leave on "official business."
    - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], Princeton, [Massachusetts], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 12 August 1872., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
      Describes their summer in the North; describes the Grand Jubilee held in Boston; describes Newport, [Maine] and the historical sites there; discusses Nina's life in the parsonage; gives news about family and friends back home.
    - Lavalette [?], "Dixie," [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 10 December 1872., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
      Says she is very happy to return from the North, though she was treated kindly there and it did improve her health; says many people at home are ill with an influenza that follows the Horse Disease; much news about family and friends.
    - Lavalette [?], Prince Edward County, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 31 July 1873., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Asks Nina how her little boy is; reveals that she thought she would be getting married this fall, but that the gentleman, Dr. Cole, has been suffering from an illness; news about family and friends.
    - "Cousin" E. S. Hopkins, Whitehall, Maryland, to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Waterford, Loudoun County, Virginia]. 26 November [1873?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Expresses hope that she will visit them in Maryland soon, and bring her child; comments on Nina's settling in Waterford, Loudon County; news of family and friends.
    - Nina [Powell Hepburn], Waterford, [Virginia?], to "Sister" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 15 February 1874., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Describes the baby Sewell's features; tells how the family is adjusting to new baby.
    - G[eorge] W[ashington] C[ustis] Lee, Lexington, Virginia, to Miss Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 27 October 1874., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Discusses tuition for Mildred.
    - Rebecca C. P[owell],[Alexandria, Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[n.p.], 22 December [post 1874]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Reports news of her school; discusses the bonds that their father sold, and his financial situation.
    - R[ebecca] C. Powell,[Alexandria, Virginia], to [Nina Powell Hepburn], n.p., [post 1874]., 4 pages. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Reports that they are taking of Uncle Lev[en], including paying for his board with Sallie Withers, and giving him clothes; expresses disappointment that other relatives are not helping him; says Uncle Lev had a drinking problem at one time and his wife will not see him.
    - "Cousin" Rebecca L. Jackson, Blacksburg, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], Waterford, [Loudoun County, Virginia], 8 January 1875., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Describes the town of Blacksburg, and the College [Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]; describes her new baby; says that when the College is on vacation, her husband must travel far to find a congregation; news about relatives.
    - Rebecca C. P[owell],[Alexandria, Virginia] to Nina [Powell Hepburn], Kent County, Maryland], 21 March 1875., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Tells Nina their plans to visit her; says they will travel through Baltimore and then by boat across the Chesapeake Bay.
    - G[eorge] W[ashington] C[ustis] Lee, New Orleans, Louisiana, to Miss Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 30 March 1875., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Sends a check for Mildred's tuition.
    - C[harles] L. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughter" [Nina Powell Hepburn], n.p., 12 May 1875., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Hopes that Mr. Hepburn has recovered from his fall and hopes he will stick to taming men's spirits rather than taming men's horses; much news about family and friends.
    - "Sister" R[ebecca] C. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Kent County, Maryland], 13 June [18]75., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Gives news about family and friends; says that they will visit her in a few weeks.
    - "Cousin" I. E. White, Edgewood, [?] to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Kent County, Maryland], 13 February [18]76., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Sends Nina a fur cape and muff; congratulates Nina on her pregnancy and hopes she feels well; sends a present for the coming baby; asks Nina for her preferred style of dress so that she can make her some.
    - "Cousin" I. E. White, Baltimore, [Maryland], to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Kent County, Maryland], 25 March [18]76., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Tells of the death of her father-in-law and the effects it has had on the family.
    - S. S. Hepburn, [Kent County, Maryland], to "Sister Beck" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 24 May 1876., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Tells of birth of another boy and that Nina is doing fine; says they have not named it because he wanted a girl; tells story of how his errand boy spilled into the well some fish he was cleaning and how he [Sewell] had to go down and fish them out.
    - Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Kent County, Maryland], 4 June [18]76., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Gives advice on how to take care of oneself after childbirth; thinks that she should have more than one servant; says that she is having some dresses made for her; news about family and friends.
    - R[ebecca] C. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn],[Fairlee, Kent County, Maryland], 11 October [1876?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Gives news of friends in Alexandria; mentions Centennial celebrations; says her school is doing well, with 21 scholars; mentions that Robert Powell has a new daughter.
    - "Sister" Rebecca C. P[owell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p. Gives news about Powell and Lee cousins in Philadelphia; says tat a few neighbors have scarlet fever; discusses politics, 11 February [18]77., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
    - Charles L. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughter" [Selina Hepburn, Fairlee, Kent County, Maryland], 9 September 1877., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Tells of his stay at Selma in Leesburg where he visited relatives; tells of weddings in Leesburg.
    - Newspaper clipping of article entitle Rev. Mr. Rainsford on Salvation by Christ, November 1877., 2 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 5:5)
    - [Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn, Kent County, Maryland], 18 March [18]79., 4 pages. AL. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Says she is glad the children are recovering from their illness; says Nina must take tonic and Lager Beer herself to say well; recommends ways to rid the house of the illness; describes a visit to Baltimore to see an art exhibit.
  - Papers, 1880-1889., 15 items. (Box-folder 5:5-6)
    - Ch[arles] L. Powell, Catlett, [Fauquier County, Virginia], to "daughter" [Nina P. Hepburn], [Kent County, Maryland], 18 August 1880., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Wishes he had a mountain house where his grandchildren could go, especially to recuperate; discusses controversy between two Churches, St. Stephens and Grace Church, in the neighborhood where he is; says they both want Mr. Jackson from Charleston, South Carolina, to be their minister.
    - R[ebecca] C. Powell, Alex[andria], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell Hepburn], n.p., 27 October 1880., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Gives a long description of her boarders and her school; gives news about neighborhood, friends and family.
    - [Rebecca C. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Sewell [Hepburn],[Kent County, Maryland], 5 November [18]80., 4 pages. AL. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Teases him about his "Destitute condition," having to take care of himself while Nina is in Baltimore; scolds him for not taking good care of himself and says she does not want Nina to become a widow; tells of a surprise visit by Mrs. Beck of his parish to visit one of her students, Hallie; discusses past election and Hancock's defeat.